曾經有一個世界
Once there was a world
它與我們的星球沒什麼不同
not so very different from our own.
偶爾會有些自然災害或者是大規模的火山爆發
There were occasional natural catastrophes, massive volcanic eruptions
時不時還會有小行星降臨在星球上砸幾個坑
and, every once in a while, an asteroid would come barreling out of the blue to do some damage.
可在最初的100萬年裏
But for the first billion years or so,
它很像是一個天堂
it would've seemed like a paradise.
這大概就是金星在太陽系還年輕時的樣子
This is what we think the planet Venus might have looked like when our solar system was young.
然後 一切就開始變得糟糕了
Then things started to go horribly wrong.
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第十二集
金星或許曾是一個天堂
The planet Venus, which once may have seemed like a heaven,
但現在卻是一個地獄
turned into a kind of hell.
造成這個差異的原因是因為有一些微妙的自然平衡被打破了
The difference between the two can be a delicate balance,
而且是比你想像中更為微妙的關係
far more delicate than you might imagine.
這個平衡一旦被打破 就再也無法挽回
Once things began to unravel, there was no way back.
這就是金星
This is what Venus,
距離我們最近的行星 今天看上去的樣子
our nearest planetary neighbor, looks like today.
金星上的海洋已經消失很久了
Venus's oceans are long gone.
星球的表面現在比燒烤爐還要燙
The surface is hotter than a broiling oven,
熱得足以融化鉛
hot enough to melt lead.
為什麼呢
Why?
你也許認為這是因為金星到太陽的距離要比地球少30%
You might think it's because Venus is 30% closer to the Sun than the Earth is,
但這不是真正的原因
but that's not the reason.
金星現在完全被硫酸雲覆蓋著
Venus is completely covered by clouds of sulfuric acid
幾乎沒有陽光可以照射到它的表面
that keep almost all the sunlight from reaching the surface.
按理來說這應該讓金星比地球更寒冷
That ought to make Venus much colder than the Earth.
但為何金星會如此的灼熱？
So why is Venus scorching hot?
那是因為有小部分的陽光
It's because the small amount of sunlight
穿過雲層抵達了地面
that trickles in through the clouds to reach the surface
卻沒能反射回去
can't get back out again.
能量不能散發是由於濃密的大氣阻隔
The flow of energy is blocked by a dense atmosphere
那就是二氧化碳
of carbon dioxide.
二氧化碳簡稱CO2
That carbon dioxide gas-- or CO2 for short--
它就像毯子一樣阻止熱量的散發
acts like a smothering blanket to keep the heat in.
沒人在金星上燒煤
No one is burning coal
或是開著大馬力的汽車在上面逛
or driving big gas-guzzlers on Venus.
自然能滅掉環境的平衡
Nature can destroy an environment
而不需要借助人的力量
without any help from intelligent life.
金星現在正處於強烈的溫室效應中
Venus is in the grip of a runaway greenhouse effect.
為什麼我們現在像是在一個碗裏？
Why does it look like we're inside a bowl?
那是因為濃密的大氣壓力
It's due to the intense atmospheric pressure.
這是金星13號的殘骸
That's the wreck of Venera 13.
1982年
In 1982, the scientists and engineers
蘇聯的科學家與工程師們
of what was then the Soviet Union
成功地將這艘探測器送到了金星
successfully landed this spacecraft on Venus.
他們設法讓飛船
They managed to keep it refrigerated
保持了2個小時以上的冷凍狀態
for overtwo hours,
讓它能給四周拍照
so it could photograph its surroundings...
並將照片傳回了地球
and transmit the images back to Earth
隨後飛船上的電子設備就燒燬了
before the on-board electronics were fried.
金星與地球在誕生初期具有相同的
Venus and Earth started out with about the same amount
碳含量 但兩個星球卻被推上了
of carbon, but the two worlds were propelled
截然不同的發展道路
along radically different paths,
碳元素在其中起到了決定性的作用
and carbon was the decisive element in both stories.
在金星 幾乎所有的大氣
On Venus, it's almost all in the form of gas--
都由二氧化碳組成
carbon dioxide-- in the atmosphere.
地球上大部分的碳已經在久遠的年代中
Most of the carbon on Earth has been stored for eons
以碳酸鹽巖的形式被儲存起來
in solid vaults of carbonate rock,
就像這一塊 它就是其中一種形式
like this one, part of a chain that forms
這就是著名的多佛海岸白色懸崖
the celebrated White Cliffs of Dover,
它位於英吉利海峽的邊上
right on the English Channel.
是哪位巨人修建了這樣的世界奇觀？
What titan built this wonder of the world?
那是一種比針頭還要小1000倍的生物
A creature a thousand times smaller than a pinhead.
數以萬億計
Trillions of them.
它叫單細胞藻類
One-celled algae.
火山將二氧化碳送入大氣後
Volcanoes supply carbon dioxide to the atmosphere,
海洋將它緩慢地吸收
and the oceans slowly absorb it.
這個過程要延續好幾百萬年
Working over the course of millions of years,
先是微小的藻類吸收了二氧化碳
the microscopic algae harvested the carbon dioxide
並將它轉化為這些小貝殼
and turned it into these tiny shells.
日積月累 最終沉積為白堊
They accumulated in thick deposits of chalk,
我們也稱之為石灰岩 它積聚在海床上
or limestone, on the ocean floor.
最終 永不停息的地殼運動將海床推起
Later, the restless Earth pushed up the sea floor
將它塑造成這些巨大的懸崖
and carved out these massive cliffs.
其他的海洋生物
Other marine creatures
用二氧化碳建造了巨大的珊瑚礁
took in carbon dioxide to build enormous coral reefs.
海洋也可以把溶解的二氧化碳轉換為石灰岩
And the oceans converted dissolved CO2 into limestone
而不需要生物的幫助
even without any help from life.
最終 只有微量的二氧化碳氣體
As a result, only a trace amount was left as a gas
留在了地球的大氣中
in Earth's atmosphere.
還不到每百分之一中的三百分之一
Not even three-hundredths of one percent.
相當於每1萬個分子中
Think of it-- fewer than three molecules
只有不到3個分子保留下來
out of every ten thousand.
而這幾個分子就是最關鍵的因素
And yet, it makes the critical difference
決定了地球是生命的樂土還是荒蕪之地
between a barren wasteland and a garden of life on Earth.
要是一點二氧化碳都沒有
With no CO2 at all,
地球將會被冰凍
the Earth would be frozen.
可要是二氧化碳的數量再多一倍
And with twice as many,
也就是像前面所說的 每1萬個分子中
we're still talking about only six molecules
有6個分子保留下來
out of ten thousand.
令人不安的炎熱就會襲來
Things would get uncomfortably hot
給人類帶來一系列的問題
and cause us some serious problems...
不過還不會像金星那麼熱 一點都不會
but never as hot as Venus; not even close.
在好幾百萬年前
That planet lost its ocean to space
這個行星上的海洋就已經消失到太空中了
billions of years ago.
沒有了海洋 它就沒有辦法從空氣中
Without an ocean, it had no way to capture CO2
捕獲二氧化碳 並將它存儲為礦物質
from the atmosphere and store it as a mineral.
從噴發的火山中產生的二氧化碳
The CO2 from erupting volcanoes
不斷地積累
just continued to build up.
時至今日 金星上的大氣要比地球重90倍
Today, that atmosphere is 90 times heavier than ours.
幾乎全部由灼熱的二氧化碳氣體組成
Almost all of it is heat-trapping carbon dioxide.
這就是為什麼金星會變成如此殘酷的地獄
That's why Venus is such a ferocious inferno
生命無法在此扎根的原因
so hostile to life.
地球則恰恰與此相反
The Earth, in stunning contrast,
它是有生命的星球
is alive.
它會呼吸
It breathes...
不過很緩慢
but very slowly.
1年才能完成1次呼吸
A single breath takes a whole year.
森林裏包含了地球上大部分的生命
The forests contain most of Earth's life,
大部分的森林都位於北半球
and most forests are in the Northern Hemisphere.
當北半球的春季到來
When spring comes to the north,
森林吸入空氣中的二氧化碳
the forests inhale carbon dioxide from the air
並隨之生長 將大地鋪滿綠色
and grow, turning the land green.
大氣中的二氧化碳含量隨之下降
The amount of CO2 in the atmosphere goes down.
秋天降臨 植物落葉 隨之枯萎
When fall comes and the plants drop their leaves, they decay,
將二氧化碳呼出到大氣中
exhaling the carbon dioxide back into the atmosphere.
同樣的過程也會發生在南半球
The same thing happens in the Southern Hemisphere
只是季節是相反的
at the opposite time of the year.
但南半球大部分是海洋
But the Southern Hemisphere is mostly ocean.
因此 是北半球的森林
So it's the forests of the north
控制了全球每年二氧化碳含量的變化
that control the annual changes in the global CO2.
地球已經像這樣呼吸了
The Earth has been breathing like this
數千萬年
for tens of millions of years.
從沒有人注意到這一點 直到1958年
But nobody noticed until 1958,
有一位海洋學家叫查爾斯•戴維•基林
when an oceanographer named Charles David Keeling
他設計了一種方法 可以精確地測量
devised a way to accurately measure
空氣中二氧化碳的含量
the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.
基林發現了地球的細微呼吸
Keeling discovered the Earth's exquisite respiration.
但他也發現了一些令人震驚的事實
But he also discovered something shocking--
有一個數字在以人類歷史上前所未有的速度上升
a rapid rise, unprecedented in human history,
那就是空氣中二氧化碳的整體水平
in the overall level of CO2,
至今這個變化還一直在繼續
one that has continued ever since.
二氧化碳水平的驚人變化
It's a striking departure from the CO2 levels that prevailed
始於農業與文明的興起時期
during the rise of agriculture and civilization.
實際上
In fact, the Earth has seen nothing like it
地球在過去的300萬年不是這個樣子
for three million years.
我們為何如此確信
How can we be so sure?
證據就記錄在水裏
The evidence is written in water.
地球保存著一份詳細的日記
The Earth keeps a detailed diary
它就寫在過去下的雪裏
written in the snows of yesteryear.
氣候科學家們鑽出冰芯
Climate scientists have drilled ice cores
從格林蘭島和南極洲的冰川深處
from the depths of glaciers in Greenland and Antarctica.
遠古的空氣被困在了冰層裏
The ice layers have ancient air trapped inside them.
我們可以閱讀到地球大氣的完整記錄
We can read the unbroken record of Earth's atmosphere
一直可以追溯到8萬年前
that extends back over the last 800,000 years.
在以往的所有時間內
In all that time,
大氣中的二氧化碳數值從沒有超過
the amount of carbon dioxide in the air never rose
每百分之一的空氣中含有三百分之一的二氧化碳
above three-hundredths of one percent.
但到了二十世紀
That is, until the turn of the 20th century.
它就開始穩定而迅速的上升並保持至今
And it's been going up steadily and rapidly ever since.
現在這個數值
It's now more than 40% higher
已經比工業革命前高出了40%
than before the Industrial Revolution.
通過燃燒煤 石油和煤氣
By burning coal, oil and gas,
人類文明在釋放出二氧化碳
our civilization is exhaling carbon dioxide
遠遠超過了地球所能吸收的速度
much faster than Earth can absorb it.
因此大氣中的二氧化碳在不斷積累
So CO2 is building up in the atmosphere.
這個星球在升溫
The planet is heating up.
每一個發熱的物體都能輻射出某種我們肉眼看不見的光
Every warm object radiates a kind of light we can't see with the naked eye--
那就是熱紅外線
thermal infrared light.
即使在黑暗中 我們的身體也能散發出不可見的熱輻射
We all glow with invisible heat radiation, even in the dark.
如果用紅外線觀察地球 它就是這個樣子
This is what the Earth looks like in the infrared.
你看到的是行星本身的發熱
You're seeing the planet's own body heat.
當陽光照射到地面
Incoming light from the Sun hits the surface.
地球本身會吸收大部分的能量
The Earth absorbs much of that energy,
讓地球升溫
which heats the planet up
從而讓地表發出紅外線
and makes the surface glow in infrared light.
但空氣中的二氧化碳
But the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
又會吸收散發出的大部分熱量
absorbs most of that outgoing heat radiation,
把這些熱量的大部分又傳回地面
sending much of it right back to the surface.
讓地球變得更熱
This makes the planet even warmer.
這就是所謂的溫室效應
That's all there is to the greenhouse effect.
它的基本物理原理
It's basic physics,
就在於把流動的能量保存下來
just bookkeeping of the energy flow.
關於它沒什麼好爭議的
There's nothing controversial about it.
如果大氣中一點二氧化碳都沒有
If we didn't have any carbon dioxide in our atmosphere,
地球就會變成一個大雪球
the Earth would just be a great big snowball,
人類也就不會存在
and we wouldn't be here.
因此 輕度的溫室效應是件好事
So, a little greenhouse effect is a good thing.
可它要是變大 就會造成氣候的不穩定
But a big one can destabilize the climate
甚至毀掉人類的生存方式
and wreck our way of life.
好吧 但我們怎麼知道人類是問題的根源？
All right... but how do we know that we're the problem?
也許是地球本身導致二氧化碳的增加
Maybe the Earth itself is causing the rise in CO2.
也許和煤與石油的燃燒無關
Maybe it has nothing to do with the coal and oil we burn.
或許是那些該死的火山
Maybe it's those damn volcanoes.
每隔幾年 西西里島的埃特納火山就會噴發
Every few years, Mount Etna, in Sicily, blows its stack.
每次的大規模噴發都會把幾百萬噸二氧化碳
Each big eruption sends millions of tons of CO2
送入空氣
into the atmosphere.
如果我們把
Now, combine that with the output
地球上所有的火山噴發合計起來的話
of all the other volcanic activity on the planet.
讓我們按最大數量進行科學預測
Let's take the largest scientific estimate--
每年大概會有5億噸二氧化碳
about 500 million tons of volcanic CO2
被送入空氣中
entering the atmosphere ever year.
聽上去很多 對不對？
Sounds like a lot, right?
可這個數值還不到人類每年產生的二氧化碳數量的2%
But that's not even two percent of the 30 billion tons of CO2
那就是1年300億噸
that our civilization is cranking out every year.
而且 還有個很有趣的現象
And, funny thing,
大氣中二氧化碳的增加量
the measured increase in CO2 in the atmosphere
與我們所知的 即是通過燃燒煤 石油和煤氣產生的二氧化碳
tallies with the known amount we're dumping there
剛好相同
by burning coal, oil and gas.
火山產生的二氧化碳有一個明顯的特徵
Volcanic CO2 has a distinct signature--
與化石燃料燃燒時產生的二氧化碳相比
it's slightly heavier than the kind produced
它要稍微重一些
by burning fossil fuels.
我們可以分辨出這兩者的差別
We can tell the difference between the two
通過對它們進行原子級別的檢驗
when we examine them at the atomic level.
檢驗結果很明顯證實 空氣中增加的二氧化碳
It's clear that the increased CO2 in the air
不是來自火山
is not from volcanoes.
更重要的是 氣候變暖的程度與
What's more, the observed warming is as much as predicted
空氣中二氧化碳增加的程度差不多
from the measured increase in carbon dioxide.
這兩者緊密關聯
It's a pretty tight case.
人類排放二氧化碳的證據都在這上面
Our fingerprints are all over this one.
每年30億噸二氧化碳到底有多少?
How much is 30 billion tons of CO2 per year?
如果我們把它壓成一個固體
If you compressed it into solid form,
它的體積就會和
it would occupy about the same volume
多佛海岸的白色懸崖差不多
as the White Cliffs of Dover.
這就是我們每年排放到空氣中的二氧化碳的數量
And we're adding that much CO2 to the air every year,
永無休止 年復一年
relentlessly, year after year.
很不幸的是
Unlucky for us, the main waste product
人類文明產生的主要垃圾產品不是物質
of our civilization is not just any substance.
而是能對全球氣候調節產生
It happens to be the chief climate-regulating gas
恆溫效果的毒氣 年年如此
of our global thermostat, year in, year out.
過多的二氧化碳就相當於看不見的毒氣
Too bad CO2 is an invisible gas.
如果我們能看到它……
Maybe if we could see it...
如果我們的眼睛能感應到二氧化碳
If our eyes were sensitive to CO2--
也許在宇宙中有這樣的生物
and perhaps there are such beings in the cosmos--
如果我們能看見二氧化碳
if we could see all that carbon dioxide,
那就沒有人能否定這一切
then we would overcome the denial
並充分瞭解到人類對大氣的嚴重影響
and grasp the magnitude of our impact on the atmosphere.
但全球變暖的證據
But the evidence that the world is getting warmer
就在我們身邊
is all around us.
首先讓我們檢查一下
For starters, let's just check the thermometers.
世界各地氣象站的溫度計
Weather stations around the world
自1880年代起
have been keeping reliable temperature records
它們一直保存著可靠的溫度記錄
since the 1880s,
美國宇航局用這些數據編製了一幅地圖
and NASA has used the data to compile a map
地圖涵蓋了所有的時間段
tracking the average temperatures
用作跟蹤世界各地平均氣溫的變化
around the world through time.
黃色意味著溫度較高
Yellow means warmer temperatures
高於1880年代任何地區的平均水平
than the average, for any region in the 1880s.
橙色意味著炎熱
Orange means hot.
紅色意味著比炎熱更熱
And red means hotter.
世界已經變得比19世紀更溫暖了
The world is warmer than it was in the 19th century.
那時 全球各地的氣溫是有史以來最均衡的
Back then, at the greatest fair the world has ever seen,
一位被遺忘的天才曾設想了一個解決問題的方案
a forgotten genius demonstrated the solution to this problem.
跟我來
Come with me.
曾經有這樣一個世界
Once there was a world
它不太熱也不太冷
that was not too hot and not too cold.
溫度適中
It was just right.
然後有一天 這裏的人們
Then there came a time when the life it sustained
開始注意到他們可愛的地球在發生變化
began to notice our lovely planet was changing.
這並不是說我們沒有預見到它的到來
And it's not as if we didn't see it coming.
早在1896年
As far back as 1896,
三十一. 關於碳酸空氣中對地面溫度的影響
瑞典科學家斯凡特•阿倫尼斯
the Swedish scientist Svante Arrhenius
通過計算發現 如果大氣中的二氧化碳含量再增加1倍
calculated that doubling the amount
大氣就如溫室一般
就能讓北極的冰融化
of CO2 in the atmosphere would melt the Arctic ice.
到了1930年代 美國物理學家E.O.赫爾伯特
In the 1930s, the American physicist E. O. Hulburt,
在海軍實驗室裏
at the Naval Research Laboratory,
確認了這個結果
confirmed that result.
二氧化碳令地球變熱
到那時為止 這一切還依然是理論
So far, it was still just theoretical.
隨後 英國工程師蓋•卡倫德
But then, the English engineer Guy Callendar
人為排放二氧化碳對於氣溫的影響
把這些證據結合起來 向人們展示
assembled the evidence to show
二氧化碳含量與全球平均氣溫
that both the CO2 and the average global temperature
都在不斷上升中
were actually increasing.
就算是現在 人們也可能在無意中改變了全球氣候
Even now, man may be unwittingly changing the world's climate
通過文明產生的廢棄物
through the waste products of his civilization.
由於人類通過工廠與汽車的排放
Due to our release, through factories
每年有超過
and automobiles every year, of more than
60億噸的二氧化碳產生
six billion tons of carbon dioxide,
讓空氣吸收了更多來自於太陽的熱量
which helps air absorb heat from the Sun,
大氣變得越來越熱
our atmosphere seems to be getting warmer.
這是不是件壞事?
This is bad?
嗯 通過計算表明
Well, it's been calculated, a few degrees rise
地球溫度的輕微升高
in the Earth's temperature
會讓地球兩極的冰帽熔化
would melt the polar ice caps.
二氧化碳與氣候
"當前的理論 假設了二氧化碳會調節地球的溫度 這就產生了一個很有趣的問題：
人類的活動如何影響未來的氣候呢？"
1960年 卡爾•薩根在他的博士論文裏
In 1960,Carl Sagan's PhD thesis
第一次計算了
included the first calculation
金星上失控的溫室效應
of the runaway greenhouse effect on Venus.
這是他職業興趣的一個部分
This was part of a career-long interest
對於行星大氣 包括我們的星球的興趣
in the atmospheres of the planets, including our own.
氣候變化:我們正處於地球變暖的邊緣嗎?
在1980製作的最初那部宇宙系列片中 卡爾•薩根警告說
In the original Cosmos series, in 1980, Carl Sagan warned...
大氣中增加的二氧化碳對氣候的影響
"我們正在釋放大量的二氧化碳
We are releasing vast quantities of carbon dioxide,
加劇了溫室效應
increasing the greenhouse effect.
用不了多久
It may not take much
地球的氣候就會失去平衡
to destabilize the Earth's climate,
把我們在宇宙中這唯一的家園 像天堂一樣的地方
to convert this heaven, our only home in the cosmos,
變為人間地獄"
into a kind of hell.
卡爾說過這些話之後
Since Carl spoke those words,
我們還在繼續加重大氣的負擔
we've burdened the atmosphere of our world with an additional
每年又多增加了4千億噸二氧化碳的排放
400 billion tons of carbon dioxide.
如果我們不改變這個現狀
If we don't change our ways,
我們未來的孩子們將會面對一個什麼樣的星球
what will the planet be like in our children's future?
根據科學研究項目的結果
Based on scientific projections,
如果我們繼續保持著現有的經濟模式不變
if we just keep on doing business as usual,
我們的子孫將會面對艱險的未來
our kids are in for a rough ride.
致命的熱浪 破紀錄的乾旱
Killer heat waves, record droughts,
不斷升高的海平面 大規模的物種滅絕
rising sea levels, mass extinction of species.
我們曾從前人手中繼承了一個富饒的世界
We inherited a bountiful world
氣候相對穩定
made possible by a relatively stable climate.
農業繁榮 文明興盛
Agriculture and civilization flourished
延續了千年之久
for thousands of years.
可現在 人類的冷漠與貪婪把這一切推向了危險的境地
And now, our carelessness and greed put all of that at risk.
好吧 如果科學家們有那麼厲害
Okay, so if we scientists are so good
可以作出關於氣候的如此長遠的可怕預測
at making these dire, long-term predictions about the climate,
那為什麼就不能把天氣測准一點呢?
How come we're so lousy about predicting the weather?
還有 今年我家鄉的冬天特別寒冷
Besides, this year, we had a colder winter in my town.
我們的科學家知不知道
For all us scientists know,
說不定我們現在面對的是全球變冷呢
we could be in for global cooling.
天氣和氣候是不同的兩個概念
Here's the difference between weather and climate...
天氣指的是短時期內的大氣變化
Weather is what the atmosphere does in the short term--
可能是幾小時 也可能是幾天
hour to hour, day to day.
天氣是變化莫測的
Weather is chaotic, which means that even
這意味著即使是微小的干擾也能引起大規模的變化
a microscopic disturbance can lead to large-scale changes.
這就是為什麼對十天後的天氣預測是沒有用的
That's why those ten-day weather forecasts are useless.
巴厘島上的一隻蝴蝶扇動了翅膀 六周以後
A butterfly flaps its wings in Bali, and six weeks later,
你在緬因州的戶外婚禮就會被狂風暴雨毀掉了
your outdoor wedding in Maine is ruined.
氣候研究的則是長時期的天氣的平均變化
Climate is the long-term average
跨越幅度有好幾年
of the weather, over a number of years.
它是由這個星球上能改變大氣能量平衡的力量決定的
It's shaped by global forces that alter the energy balance
比如說 陽光的變化
in the atmosphere, such as changes in the Sun,
地球自轉軸的傾斜度
the tilt of the Earth's axis,
地球反射回太空的日照量
the amount of sunlight the Earth reflects back to space
空氣中的溫室氣體濃度
and the concentration of greenhouse gases in the air.
它們當中任何一個的變化都能影響氣候
A change in any of them affects the climate
而且它們的變化方式是大致可以預測的
in ways that are broadly predictable.
我的這位小朋友忽左忽右的走路方式
My friend's meandering
就好比是短期的波動
represents the short-term fluctuations--
這就是天氣
that's weather.
基本上很難預測
It's almost impossible to predict
誰知道它等會兒又會對什麼感興趣
what'll attract his interest next,
不過我們不難知道它遊蕩的範圍
but not hard to know what the range of his meandering will be,
因為我用皮帶牽著它
because I'm holding him on a leash.
人不能直接觀察到氣候
We can't observe climate directly--
因為我們所見的是天氣
all we see is the weather--
但經過好幾年後推算出的平均天氣變化
but the average weather, over the course of years,
會揭示出一個模式
reveals a pattern.
這就是一個長期的趨勢
I represent that long-term trend,
這就是氣候
which is climate.
把注意力放在人身上 別看狗
Keep your eye on the man, not the dog.
天氣很難預測 就像我的這位小朋友
Weather is hard to predict, like my friend here,
但氣候是可以預測的
but climate is predictable.
在地球漫長的歷史上 氣候曾經變換過好多次
Climate has changed many times in the long history of the Earth
每一次都是受某種全球性力量作用的結果
but always in response to a global force.
現在影響氣候變化最強的力量就是
The strongest force driving climate change right now
由於燃燒化石燃料而不斷增加的二氧化碳
is the increasing CO2 from the burning of fossil fuels,
它留住了更多的太陽熱量
which is trapping more heat from the Sun.
這些多出來的能量必須有個去處
All that additional energy has to go somewhere.
有些能量讓空氣升溫
Some of it warms the air.
大部分的能量則被海洋吸收
Most of it ends up in the oceans.
全世界的海洋現在都在變暖
All over the world, the oceans are getting warmer.
最明顯的就是北冰洋
It's most obvious in the Arctic Ocean
以及它周圍的陸地
and the lands that surround it.
好吧 如果說我們正在失去一些夏季的海冰
Okay, so we're losing the summer sea ice
不過那個地方又是沒什麼人去的
in a place where hardly anyone ever goes.
我幹嘛要關心北極有沒有冰呢？
What do I care if there's no ice around the North Pole?
冰是地球最亮的自然表面
Ice is the brightest natural surface on the Earth,
廣闊的海洋則是最暗的自然表面
and open ocean water is the darkest.
冰能把陽光反射回太空
Ice reflects incoming sunlight back to space.
水則會吸收陽光而變暖
Water absorbs sunlight
這會讓更多的冰融化
and gets warmer, which melts even more ice,
讓更多的海洋水面暴露出來
which exposes still more ocean surface
並吸收更多的陽光
to absorb even more sunlight.
這就是所謂的正反饋效應
This is what we call a positive feedback loop.
這是能把二氧化碳引起的熱效應放大的
It's one of many natural mechanisms that magnify
許多種自然機制中的一個
any warming caused by CO2 alone.
我們現在是在阿拉斯加的德魯角
We're at Drew Point, Alaska,
這裏是北冰洋的邊緣
on the edge of the Arctic Ocean.
當我出生的時候 這裏的海岸線伸出去有1英里多
When I was born, the shoreline was a mile farther out,
它過去曾以每年20英尺的速度縮減
and it was breaking off at a rate of about 20 feet per year.
現在……
Now...
縮減的速度達到了每年50英尺
it's being eaten away at about 50 feet per year.
北冰洋正在變暖
The Arctic Ocean is warming
而且變暖的速度在不斷增快
and at an increasing rate.
所以每年裏有大部分時間這裏是沒有冰的
So it's ice-free during more of the year.
有更多的海岸線因此暴露出來
That leaves the shore here
被風暴所侵蝕
more exposed to erosion from storms,
這讓另一種力量變得更強大
which are also getting more powerful,
這種力量能影響氣候的變化
another effect of climate change.
阿拉斯加北部 西伯利亞 加拿大
The northern reaches of Alaska, Siberia and Canada
這些地方的大部分是永久性凍土
are mostly permafrost,
地面被凍結超過千年
ground that has been frozen year-round for millennia.
它裏面含有很多有機質
It contains lots of organic matter,
過去的樹葉與樹根
old leaves and roots from plants
它們曾生長在數千年前
that grew thousands of years ago.
由於北冰洋地區的升溫速度在加快
Because the Arctic regions are warming faster
比地球上其他地區都要快
than anywhere else on Earth,
永久性凍土開始融化
the permafrost is thawing
凍土中的東西開始腐爛
and its contents are rotting,
效果就和冰箱斷電差不多
just like when you unplug the freezer.
融化的凍土釋放出二氧化碳
The thawing permafrost is releasing carbon dioxide
還有甲烷 這是一種更厲害的的溫室氣體
and methane, an even more potent greenhouse gas,
它們都進入了大氣中
into the atmosphere.
這讓世界變得更熱
This is making things even warmer,
還有一個正反饋效應的例子
another example of a positive feedback mechanism.
世界的永久性凍土層中儲存有大量的碳
The world's permafrost stores enough carbon
足以讓大氣中的二氧化碳再增加一倍
to more than double the CO2 in the atmosphere.
按照現在的速度
At the rate we're going,
全球變暖很快就要實現大部分了
global warming could release most of it
時間就是本世紀末
by the end of the century.
人類也許正在將氣候推上一條不歸路
We might be tipping the climate past a point of no return
讓它走向無法預知的一面
into an unpredictable slide.
好吧 如果空氣 水 陸地
Okay, the air, the water
還有其他的一切都變暖了
and the land are all getting warmer,
全球變暖真的發生了
so global warming is really happening.
也許這不是人類的錯
But maybe it's not our fault.
也許這是自然造成的
Maybe it's just nature.
也許是因為太陽
Maybe it's the Sun.
不 也許不是因為太陽
No, it's not the Sun.
我們這幾十年來一直在密切的觀測太陽
We've been monitoring the Sun very closely for decades,
而太陽輸送的能量一直都沒有變過
and the solar energy output hasn't changed.
還有 地球現在是
What's more, the Earth is warming more at night
晚上比白天更暖
than in daytime,
冬天比夏天更暖
and more in winter than in summer.
這是符合溫室效應規律的
That's exactly what we expect from greenhouse warming,
與太陽輸送能量的增加
but the opposite of what increased solar output
一點關係都沒有
would cause.
懷疑是沒有用的 現在的一切清楚表明
It's now clear beyond any reasonable doubt
人類正在改變氣候
that we are changing the climate.
太陽根本就不是元兇
The Sun isn't the problem.
而拯救這一切的方案
But it is the solution,
人類早已制備了很久
and we've known this for a long time,
早在比你想像中更久遠的年代
much longer than you might think.
巴黎 1878年9月
Paris, September 1878.
埃菲爾鐵塔還要過好多年才會開始建造
The Eiffel Tower won't be built for years to come.
世博會
世界上最壯觀非凡的景象
the world has ever seen.
自由女神像宏偉的頭部
The magnificent head of the Statue of Liberty
才剛剛造好
has just been completed.
全球各地數千家展商
Thousands of exhibitors from around the planet
在巴黎的66英畝土地上
covered 66 acres of Paris
佈滿了他們的發明與產品
with their inventions and goods.
愛迪生發明的燈泡還要在好幾年後才
Edison's first public demonstration of the light bulb
第一次向公眾展示
will not take place for another year.
電氣設備還沒有出現
There's no such thing as electrical appliances.
人們還不會開開關 按按鈕
People don't flick switches and press buttons.
這是一個人牽馬拉的世界
It's a hand-cranked, horse-drawn world.
這就是我們要說到的那個人
That's the guy we came to see,
那個有奇怪鬍子的人
the one with the crazy moustache.
他是一個數學老師 名叫奧古斯丁•莫超
He's a math teacher named Augustin Mouchot.
記住 這是在1878年
Remember, it's 1878.
一個由煤氣燈統治的世界
This is a world lit mostly by gaslight.
汽車還要過好多年才會發明
The automobile is still years away.
但莫超的發明足以讓觀眾目瞪口呆
But Mouchot, here, is dazzling the crowd
那是一個太陽能聚能設備
with his solar power concentrator.
太陽屬於我們每一個人
The Sun belongs to all of us!
就算它距離我們1億5千萬公里遠
Even though it is 150 million kilometers away from us,
感受一下它那強悍的威力吧
feel its awesome power!
我的發明能把太陽散發的免費的能量集中起來
My invention concentrates the free energy of the Sun
把它轉化為機械運動
and converts it into mechanical motion.
為任何一種機器提供能量
It can power any kind of machine.
它可以用來發電或者是讓印刷機運轉
It can produce electricity or run a printing press
甚至是在熱天製冰
or make ice on a hot day.
等著瞧吧
Et voila !
想想吧
Think of it,
既然陽光能轉化為冰塊
sunlight converted into ice.
想想吧 朋友們 如果我們能把豐富的太陽能利用起來
You see, my friends, what wonders we can work
我們能做出什麼樣的奇跡來
if we harness the bounteous energy of the Sun.
世界上的煤總有一天會用完
The world will someday run out of coal,
但輝煌的太陽永遠在那裏照耀著我們
but the magnificent Sun will always be there for us.
莫超獲得了這一屆世界博覽會的金獎
Mouchot took home the gold medal from the fair.
但煤炭的價格下跌了
But the price of coal tumbled,
價格如此之低以至於人們對太陽能再也沒有興趣
becoming so cheap that there was no interest in solar energy.
此外 當時還沒有人明白
Besides, no one understood, back then,
燃燒化石燃料的真正代價是什麼
what the true cost was of burning fossil fuel.
莫超的研究經費被砍掉了
Mouchot's research funding was cut off.
35年後 也就是二十世紀初期
35 years later, in the early years of the 20th century,
通向另一個未來的另一扇大門被打開了
another door opened to an alternative future.
它發生在埃及 尼羅河岸邊
It happened in Egypt, on the banks of the Nile.
未來的時間旅行者們記住了
Memo to future time travelers...
這是一個對避免氣候變化而言
this would be an excellent entry point
絕佳的起點
for averting climate change.
1913年 埃及
Egypt, 1913.
這是來自美國費城的弗蘭克•舒曼
That's Frank Shuman of Philadelphia.
他只讀過3年書
He's only had three years of schooling,
但他天才的創造發明能力彌補了這一切
but his genius for innovation more than makes up for that.
在30歲以前 舒曼發明了安全玻璃
Before he was 30, Shuman had invented safety glass.
它被廣泛用在汽車與飛機上 挽救了無數的生命
Its use in automobiles and skylights saved countless lives
也讓他變得非常有錢
and made him a very rich man,
有錢 讓他能去追求自己真正的夢想
rich enough to pursue his real passion,
太陽能
solar energy.
舒曼領導著一支團隊設計並建造了
Shuman led the team that designed and built
一組太陽能聚能設備
an array of solar energy concentrators.
它能驅動蒸汽機
It could power a steam engine.
舒曼希望利用太陽能
Shuman is hoping to use the Sun's power
以灌溉沙漠
to irrigate the desert
讓它重新變綠
and turn it green.
舒曼的太陽能發電站
The official inauguration
在1913年正式啟動
of Shuman's solar power plant, in 1913,
這是個了不起的成就
was a dazzling success.
他發明了一種實用的方法
He had invented a practical way to tap the Sun's energy
讓太陽能得以實現工業規模的應用
on an industrial scale,
讓太陽能比煤更便宜
making solar energy even cheaper than coal.
英德兩國政府
The British and German governments
給予了舒曼慷慨的贊助
both offered Shuman generous funding
讓他去創造發明
to develop his invention.
這是一種理想的豐富的能量來源
It was the ideal source of abundant power
尤其是在熱帶地區
in tropical regions,
那裏進口煤的價格比較昂貴
where imported coal was prohibitively expensive.
但舒曼有更大的夢想
But Shuman was dreaming even bigger.
在給《科學美國人》寫的一封信中
In a letter to Scientific American,
他對他的太陽能發電廠進行了計算
he calculated that his solar power plants,
如果能將它安裝在一個像撒哈拉沙漠那樣的地區
if deployed in an area of the Sahara Desert
只需要方圓150英里的面積 就能提供
only 150 miles on a side, could supply as much power
足以讓世界所有工廠消費的能量
as consumed by all the industries of the world.
但這一切最終沒有發生
But it was not to be.
石油 這種液體化石燃料的市場
The market for a liquid fossil fuel, petroleum,
隨船運而蓬勃發展起來
was exploding for shipping,
家庭供熱 汽車與卡車
home heating, and cars and trucks.
石油很豐富 甚至比煤還便宜
Oil was abundant, cheaper even than coal,
它很容易就能獲得 易於加工
and much easier to get out of the ground and process.
要把煤裝滿一艘船 需要100個人幹上1周
It took 100 men a week to fuel a ship with coal,
但如果是裝石油
but with oil, one man could do the job
1個人幹上1天就可以了
in a single day.
舒曼在沙漠中取得成功後的第2年
A year after Shuman's triumph in the desert,
第一次世界大戰爆發
World War I broke out.
他的太陽能集熱器被回收 變成了武器
His solar collectors were recycled into weapons.
舒曼夢想中的太陽能發電的文明社會
Frank Shuman's dream of a solar-powered civilization
只有等到下一個世紀
would have to wait another century
才能獲得重生的機遇
before it was reborn.
在我們這個世界上
There's another inexhaustible source of clean energy
還有另一種取之不盡的清潔能源
for the world.
風能本身也是由太陽能產生的
The winds themselves are solar-powered,
太陽驅動著風與波浪
because our star drives the winds and the waves.
與太陽能集熱器不同
Unlike solar collectors,
風能發電廠只需要很少的土地
wind farms take up very little land,
如果是在海邊 那就一點陸地都用不到
and none at all, if offshore,
海上的風力是最強的
where the winds are strongest.
如果人類能把世界上百分之一的風能利用起來
If we could tap even one percent of their power,
就會有充足的能源供文明社會運作
we'd have enough energy to run our civilization.
而每個小時落在地球上的太陽能量
And more solar energy falls on Earth in one hour
都超過我們人類社會
than all the energy our civilization consumes
1年消費的能量總和
in an entire year.
只要人類能把很小一部分
If we could harness a tiny fraction
可用的太陽能與風能利用起來
of the available solar and wind power,
人類就會有永久充足的能源供應
we could supply all our energy needs forever,
而無需向大氣中排放任何的碳
and without adding any carbon to the atmosphere.
現在時猶未晚
It's not too late.
未來仍值得我們奮鬥
There's a future worth fighting for.
為何我能這樣肯定？
How do I know?
我們每個人都是艱苦鬥爭後的倖存者
Every one of us comes from a long line of survivors.
如果不懂得適應環境 人類這個物種就不會存在
Our species is nothing if not adaptive.
因為我們的先人學會了
It was only because our ancestors learned
目光長遠 應時而動
to think long-term, and act accordingly,
人類才會有今天
that we're here at all.
前有困阻 但我們不能退避
We've had our backs to the wall before,
我們要邁向新的高度
and we came through to scale new heights.
實際上 人類歷史上所取得的很多偉大的成就
In fact, the most mythic human accomplishments of all
都是來自最黑暗的時刻
came out of our darkest hour.
曾經有這樣一個世界
Once there was a world
6萬枚核武器如箭在弦上 時刻待發
rigged with 60,000hair-triggered nuclear weapons.
這場廝殺發生在
The combatants were
地球上兩個最強大的國家之間
the two most powerful countries on Earth,
他們死也要纏在一起
and they were locked in a deadly embrace,
每一個國家都宣稱
each vowing that they would rather see
寧願讓這個世界玉石俱焚
everything we love destroyed
也不要不讓別人得到她
than submit to the will of the other.
當時我才3歲
When I was three years old,
有史以來威力最強的人造炸彈
the largest man-made explosion of all time
剛由蘇聯引爆
was detonated by the Soviet Union.
舊的恐懼剛剛消退 新的恐懼隨之而來
That terror has subsided, to be replaced by new fears.
地球上2000個最大的城市
The danger that the 2,000 largest cities on Earth
隨時會有在一個下午內化為廢墟的危險
would be reduced to rubble in the space of an afternoon
但跟這個比都算不上什麼
is no longer one of them.
美國與蘇聯之間的
The nuclear rivalry between the United States
核軍備競賽
and the Soviet Union
創造了一個副產品
had another by-product.
阿波羅登月計劃
The Apollo missions to the Moon were an extension
就是美蘇間軍備競爭的產物
of the arms race that raged between them.
把人送上地球軌道
Sending people to orbit the Earth
或是送到月球 都需要大型的 可靠的
or go to the Moon requires big, reliable,
大推力火箭 而這正是
powerful rockets-- precisely the same technology
攜帶核彈頭所需的科技
you need to carry a nuclear warhead
讓它可以飛越半個地球
halfway around the planet
摧毀敵國的最大城市
to destroy your enemy's largest cities.
我相信這個國家
"I believe that this nation
一定會達成這個目標
should commit itself to achieving the goal,
那就是在未來的十年裏 把人送上月球
before this decade is out, of landing a man on the Moon
並讓他安全的返回地球
and returning him safely to the Earth."
肯尼迪總統1961年的演講
President Kennedy's 1961 speech
讓這個國家興奮起來
electrified the nation,
裏面提到了很多讓人印象深刻的遠景計劃
and it contained much that was remarkably prophetic--
但在關於探月計劃的內容中
but not a word about a scientific objective
沒有一個字是跟科學項目有關的
for going to the Moon.
沒有關於對月球起源的探索
No questions about the Moon's origin
或是帶回樣品進行分析的想法
or the hope of bringing back samples to analyze.
阿波羅計劃與科學無關 它原本就是為了
No, the Apollo missions were conceived
展示超級大國的實力
as a demonstration of the superior power
以及戰術導彈的精度
and precision of our strategic missiles.
但可笑的是
But a funny thing happened to us...
在探月的道路上
on our way to the Moon.
當人類回望故鄉時
We looked homeward...
卻發現了另一個世界
and discovered another world--
我們自己的世界
our own.
第一次 我們這些地球的居民
For the first time, we inhabitants of Earth
可以後退一步 看看地球到底是什麼樣子
could step back and see it as it really is--
這是一個不可分割的世界
one world, indivisible,
在浩瀚的宇宙中它是如此的渺小
and kind of small in the cosmic context.
不管是為了什麼原因 讓我們集結了大量的資源
Whatever the reason we first mustered the enormous resources
投入到阿波羅計劃上
required for the Apollo program,
不管冷戰時期的我們是如何深陷民族主義的思潮
however mired it was in Cold War nationalism
以及對殺人武器的追求
and the instruments of death,
我們仍不可避免地認識到了
the inescapable recognition of the unity
地球是脆弱而不可分割的統一體
and fragility of the Earth
每一個明亮發光的點都是它的組成部分
is its clear and luminous dividend,
這是阿波羅計劃的意外收穫
the unexpected gift of Apollo.
一個致力於死亡競賽的項目
A project conceived in deadly competition
讓我們認識了這個地球共同體
made us recognize our community.
是什麼樣的巨人修建了這個世界奇觀？
What titan built this wonder of the world?
是菲律賓伊富高省的人民
It was the Ifugao people of the Philippines,
依靠著他們的雙手辛勤勞作
working with not much more than their hands.
在大約1萬年前 我們在世界各地的祖先
About 10,000 years ago, our ancestors all over the world
利用了另一種形式的氣候突變
took advantage of another form of climate change,
冰河時代間歇期中出現的溫和天氣
the gentler climate of the intermission in the ice age--
他們發明了農業
they invented agriculture.
他們放棄了無休止的
They gave up the ceaseless wandering,
流浪 遊獵以及採集的生活方式
hunting and gathering that had been their way of life
這種方式曾延續了1百萬年之久
for a million years or so,
他們定居下來 生產食物
to settle down and produce food.
他們發現耕作農田
They found a way to harvest
能讓他們比先人通過自然環境
ten to a hundred times more solar energy
獲得要高出十到百倍之多的太陽能
than the environment naturally provided for their ancestors.
世界各地的人們艱難地實現了
People all over the world made the difficult transition
從遊牧文化向農耕文化的轉變
from nomadic cultures to agricultural ones
這是一種更有效的使用太陽能的方式
that used solar energy more efficiently.
這讓文明興盛起來
It gave rise to civilization.
我們就站在那些辛勤勞作的先人的肩上
We stand on the shoulders of those who did the hard work
他們為我們實現最基礎的轉變
that such a fundamental transformation required.
現在 該輪到我們了
Now... it's our turn.
曾經有這樣一個世界……
Once there was a world...
如果在金星上曾有過生命 他們也不會有機會
If life ever existed on Venus, it would have had no chance
扭轉這個世界走向地獄的命運
to avert the hellish destiny of this world.
這種失控的溫室效應是無法阻擋的
This runaway greenhouse effect was unstoppable.
曾經
Once...
有這樣一個世界
there was a world...
那是我們的世界
ours.
就是現在的世界
And that world is now.
沒有任何科學或技術上的障礙
There are no scientific or technological obstacles
會阻止我們保護這個世界
to protecting our world
保護這個世界上珍貴的生命
and the precious life that it supports.
一切都取決於
It all depends...
我們真正珍惜的是什麼
on what we truly value...
我們能否付諸於行動
and if we can summon the will to act.
"為什麼" 有人問 為什麼要選擇月亮
But why, some say, the Moon?
為什麼把它作為我們的目標？
Why choose this as our goal?
他們也許還會問
And they may well ask,
我們為什麼要登上世界的最高峰？
why climb the highest mountain?
而我們選擇了登月
We choose to go to the Moon...
我們選擇了在十年內登月
...we choose to go to the Moon in this decade
我們還要做其他的事情
and do the other things,
不是因為它們很容易 而是因為它們很難
not because they are easy, but because they are hard.
中文翻譯 幸福的微笑 timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息